Herrick B. Young papers, 1925-1984 C109
Indiana University Archives
Herrick B. Young papers
1925-1984
1935-1970
Indiana University Archives
Young, Herrick B. (Herrick Black), 1904-
C109
2.8 cubic feet 4 boxes
Herrick B. Young was an Indiana University alumnus, 1925. After leaving IU, Young continued his schooling elsewhere and became an English and literature professor at Alborz College in Tehran, Iran. He later became President of the Western College for Women in Oxford, Ohio, 1954-1969, and served as President of the Near East Foundation, 1972-1976. He was a Fellow of the Royal Geographic Society and the Royal Central Asian Society, and held two honorary doctorates. This collection contains memoirs of Young's travels and scrapbooks and articles written by Young between the 1920s and 1980s. The collection also contains lectures, notes, correspondence, and Young's book, Strange lands and wonderful people.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Herrick B. Young was born on February 8, 1904 and died on February 15, 1990. Young obtained three degrees: A.B. in English from Indiana University in 1925, a M.A. in Indo-Iranian Studies from Columbia University in 1928, and a Ph.D. in Education Administration from the University of Pennsylvania in 1936. Upon receiving his A.B., Young went to Tehran, Iran. There he taught English and Literature at Alborz College. While in Iran he met his future wife, Charlotte, who he married in 1928.
From 1936 to 1950 Young was the Executive Secretary of the Presbyterian Board of Foreign Missions, and in this position traveled extensively to Africa, China, Japan, the Philippines, the Middle East, South America and southern Europe. From 1950-1953, Young was Executive Director of the International House, Inc., and from 1954-1969, Young served as President of the Western College for Women. In 1972, Young became President of the Near East Foundation. In the late 1970s, the Youngs returned to the United States and settled in Mt. Pleasant, Ohio, with a winter residence in Florida.
During his lifetime, Young published nine books, thirty articles, and was managing editor of a magazine. Young also received numerous awards and honors including being named a Fellow of the Royal Geographic Society and of the Royal Central Asian Society, awarded honorary doctorates from two universities, served as a trustee and board member of numerous institutions, and was recipient of the Institute of International Education Award and of the Reader's Digest Foundation Award.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Subject files, Correspondence, and Writings.
Scope and Content Note
The Herrick B. Young papers comprise 2.8 cubic feet and span the period from 1925 to 1984. The collection is organized into three series: Subject files, Correspondence, and Writings.
The first series is entitled Subject files. This series consists of twenty-one folders arranged alphabetically and spanning the years 1925-1982. Of special interest are Young's memoirs of trips to Africa (1945 and 1958), Iran and the Middle East (1925-1933), and Latin America (1936-1939), and a scrapbook of clippings and other publications compiled by Young from the 1920s to the 1980s.
Correspondence is the second series. This series consists of fifty-one folders arranged chronologically and spanning the years 1925-1984. The majority of the papers in this series consist of letters from Young to his family and friends written during his extensive travels. The letters from 1933 include a letter mentioning Teddy Roosevelt's visit to Teheran and how Young was able to meet him at a legation tea.
The final series in the collection is entitled Writings. This series consists of thirty-six files arranged chronologically and spanning the years from 1927-1975. In addition to his books, articles and reviews, the collection contains addresses, lectures, and notes compiled for his publications as well as a biographical essay written by John T. Fares about the life of Herrick B. Young. Included in the collection is his book Strange Lands and Wonderful People. Prominent subjects in Young's writings include religion, Middle Eastern culture, and education.
Acquisition Information
Accessions 9190-9192
Strange lands and wonderful people.; Young, Herrick B. (Herrick Black), 1904- -- Archives; Young, Herrick B. (Herrick Black), 1904- -- Correspondence; Young, Herrick B. (Herrick Black), 1904- -- Strange lands and wonderful people
- Subject files, 1925-1982
  - Africa, April 19-July 9, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Africa H. B. Y. Memories File, 1945; 1958 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Sketch, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Chile Reports/Poems, December 1938; February 1940 (Box 1)
  - Church Bulletins -- Dr. Young as Guest Speaker (Box 1)
    - 1942-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949-1977 (Box 1)
  - Clippings/China, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    General
    Not about Dr. Young
  - Clippings about Herrick Young (Box 1)
    - 1925-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946-1980 (Box 1)
  - Cumberland Death Pamphlet, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Family-H. B. Y. Memories File, 1925-1953 (Box 1)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Iran & Middle East H. B. Y. Memories File, 1925-1933 (Box 1)
  - Latin America H. B. Y. Memories File, 1936-1939; 1942-1946; 1952 (Box 1)
  - Latin America Brief Journal, July 14-December 10, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Photos, 1955-? (Box 1)
  - Seceder Cemetery & Its Background, April 9, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Western College for Women (Box 1)
    - Presidential Inauguration, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Presidential Letters, Incomplete, February 1955-December 1966 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Regarding, January 1978 (Box 1)
    - Retirement From/Letters, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1925-1984
  - June-December 1925 (Box 1)
    Traveling to & residing in Tehran
  - 1926 (Box 1)
    Tehran
  - 1927 (Box 1)
    Enroute home from Persia
  - General correspondence, 1928 (Box 1)
  - June-July 1929 (Box 1)
    From Persia
  - General correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1930 (Box 1)
    - 1931 (Box 1)
    - 1932 (Box 1)
    - 1933 (Box 1)
  - 1934 (Box 1)
    From Tehran
  - General correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1935 (Box 1)
    - &, 1936; May 3, 1937 (Box 1)
    - 1938 (Box 1)
    - 1939 (Box 2)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - 1942 (Box 2)
    - 1943 (Box 2)
  - 1944 (Box 2)
    From Scarsdale, N.Y.
  - 1945 (Box 2)
    From N.Y., Africa, Miami
  - General correspondence, 1946 (Box 2)
  - 1947 (Box 2)
    From N.Y., Korea, Japan
  - 1948 (Box 2)
    U.S. Travels
  - General correspondence, 1949 (Box 2)
  - 1950 (Box 2)
  - 1951 (Box 2)
    From N.Y., CA., PA., Latin America
  - 1952 (Box 2)
    From N.Y., Florida, Montreal
  - 1953 (Box 2)
    Europe & Asia trip
  - 1954 (Box 2)
    From Rome, Calcutta, Honolulu
  - General correspondence (Box 2)
    - December 1955 (Box 2)
    - 1956 (Box 2)
    - 1957 (Box 2)
  - 1958 (Box 2)
    Africa
  - General correspondence (Box 2)
    - January-March 1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
  - July-August 1961 (Box 2)
    Far East Seminar, Mrs. Young's death (mother)
  - General correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
  - 1967 (Box 2)
    House Pilgrimage
  - General correspondence (Box 2)
    - 1968 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    NEF Letters-misc./related items
  - 1974 (Box 2)
    From Middle East & Africa
  - 1977 (Box 2)
    From Florida, N.Y., Mt. Pleasant
  - August-September 1977 (Box 2)
    C.E.Y. memories
  - General correspondence (Box 2)
    - January-May 1978 (Box 2)
    - June-September 1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
  - 1983 (Box 2)
    re: Nominee-Stone Award
  - General correspondence, 1984 (Box 2)
- Writings, 1927-1975
  - The Red Book edited by HBY, 1923-1924 (Box 2)
  - The Vagabond HBY managing editor, 1925 (Box 2)
  - Personal writings, stories, and related Items, 1927-1933 (Box 2)
  - "Into Soviet Land by Air," "Pedagogy in Persia," "Persia Faces Forward," by HBY in Delta Chi Quarterly, 1928; 1929; 1936 (Box 2)
  - English Book 1st & 2nd editions, edited by HBY, 1930-1933 (Box 2)
  - "Persia's Newspapers Today," by HBY, in The Quill, 1931 (Box 2)
  - "Browning in Persia," by HBY, in School and Society, 1933 (Box 2)
  - "A Trip To Kermanshah," by HBY, in Indiana University Alumni Quarterly, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Personal writings, stories and related Items, 1934-1937 (Box 2)
  - "Plumbing in Persia," by HBY, in Plumbing and Heating Magazine, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Rustam in Teheran, by HBY, 1935 (Box 3)
  - "Times Have Changed," by HBY, in Women and Missions, 1935 (Box 3)
  - "Mahmood Decemberides for Christ", "On to Mastto Grosso," by HBY, in Five Continents, 1936; 1940 (Box 3)
  - "The Colorful Career of Herrick B. Young," by John T. Fares, in Forward, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Islam Awakens, by HBY, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Moslem Editors Say, by HBY, 1937 (Box 3)
  - "The Foreign Missionary Today," by HBY, in Indiana Alumni Magazine, 1938 (Box 3)
  - "The Function of the Future Missionary," by HBY, in Christian World Facts, 1938 (Box 3)
  - "The Future Foreign Missionary," by HBY, in The Presbyterian Tribune, 1939 (Box 3)
  - One Great Fellowship, by HBY, 1939 (Box 3)
  - Papers, by HBY, 1939-1982 (Box 3)
  - Travel letters and reports, by HBY &, 1939; 1945; 1947 (Box 3)
  - "The University Christian Mission," by HBY, in The Presbyterian, 1939 (Box 3)
  - The Future Missionary to the Moslems, by HBY, 1941 (Box 3)
  - "Missions and the War""The Frontier is Everywhere," by HBY, in The Intercollegian, 1942; 1951 (Box 3)
  - "The Foreign Missionary Today," by HBY, in The Presbyterian Survey, 1942 (Box 3)
  - "Road to Latin Americans" "European Glimpses," "South of the Rio Grande," by HBY, in International House Quarterly, 1942; 1950; 1951 (Box 3)
  - Religious Digest, by HBY, 1943 (Box 3)
  - Western College Convocation Addresses and Lectures, by HBY, 1954-1969 (Box 3)
  - Western College Seminar Letters and Logs, by HBY, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Back cover of Delta Chi Quarterly, photo of HBY, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Tuesday Mornings in Kumler Chapel; A collection of Chapel talks delivered at Western College for Women by Dr. Herrick B. Young during the past ten years of his presidency, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Negro Literature, writings on, by HBY, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Strange Lands and Wonderful People, by HBY, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Educational Theories of Sa'di, the Persian, by HBY, undated (Box 4)
  - Memoirs and Letters of Charlotte Elizabeth Young, 1895-1982, foreword by HBY, undated (Box 4)